你好,学生
hello students
我是Yan，今天我们讨论一些基础知识
I'm Yan and today we're going to be talking about some fundamentals
特别是Linux进程加载的基础知识
specifically fundamentals of Linux process loading
这是基础知识系列中的一个
this is an entry of our fundamental series
你应该已经掌握这些知识
of knowledge that you should already have
才能继续后面的课程
to be able to approach the rest of this course
如果知识上有空白
just in case there are gaps in the knowledge
希望这节课能填补上
hopefully this lecture will fill them in
抱歉
excuse me
好的
all right
开工吧
let's roll
我们将使用/bin/cat作为本课的示例程序
we're gonna be using /bin/cat as an example program for this lecture
/bin/cat程序，从一个地方读入数据
/bin/cat is a program that reads in data from one source
然后输出到标准输出
and spews it out to standard output
我展示一下我写的/bin/cat的替代品
let me show you a replacement for /bin/cat that I wrote
用它更方便观察发生了什么
so we have an easier time of tracking what is going on
它很简单
it's quite simple
就在这儿，只有6行
here it is just 6 lines
包括C代码中的花括号等等
including curly brackets and so forth of C code
也许是7或8行，我没数
maybe 7 or 8 I'm not counting
它只是打开一个文件
that simply opens a file
如果没指定文件，则使用标准输入
or use a standard input if files isn't specified
有数据输入，就输出
and continually while there's data reads it and writes it
又好又简单
nice and simple
好的
all right
我们来讲讲这个文件的生命周期
let's roll with the lifecycle of this file
我们先从进程的创建开始
we'll start with process creation
一直到进程终结
we'll end with process termination
以及这中间发生的全部内容
and we'll cover everything in between
本节课，我们将覆盖这前3个加载及初始化的部分
in this lecture we'll cover these first three kind of the loading initialization parts
先从进程的创建开始
starting from process creation
进程到底是什么
so what the heck is a process
我们一直用这个词
we keep using this term
这个词当然是有含义的
and the term of course has meanings
你电脑上的每一个程序
every individual program on your computer
当它运行时，或多或少都是作为一个进程运行
when it runs runs as a process right more or less
你的浏览器是一个进程
so your browser is a process
实际上，现代浏览器通常每个标签页都有一个进程
actually modern browsers have generally speaking one process per tab
插件用额外的进程
with additional processes for plugins
这是一种安全措施
this is a security measure
启动的终端，是一个进程
a terminal when you launch it is a process
微软的Word是一个进程，等等
Microsoft Word is a process and so on
当然它不运行在Linux上，但这个论据没问题
of course not on Linux but the point stands
每个Linux进程都有一些属性
every Linux process has a number of attributes that
一些是安全相关的
it contains some of which are security relevance
一些是内核用来监控状态的，等等
and some of which the kernel uses to figure out what the hell is going on and so on
这些属性是像当前进程状态之类的
these attributes at a very high level are stuff like the current process state
像进程在运行吗
is the process running
进程在等待资源吗
is the process waiting on some resource to become available
进程停止了吗
is the process stopped
如果你在shell中按Ctrl Z
if you hit Ctrl Z in your shell
会把进程放在后台，并停止
it'll background the process and stop it
然后你可以用shell内置的fg恢复它
and then you can use the fg shell built in to resume it
进程的优先级是高，还是低
does the process have a high low  or what is the priority of the process
它有助于内核调度进程
this helps the kernel schedule a process
当然，任意时刻都有很多进程在运行
of course you have a lot of processes running at any point in the time
你的计算机可能是2核的、4核的或8核的
your laptop or desktop might have 2,4,8 cores
大量的进程需要
and your huge population processes needs to
在不同时间点调度到这些核上
get scheduled at various times among your computing cores
这样所有进程才能正常运行
so that everything runs
内核使用进程状态信息或调度信息来解决这个问题
the kernel uses process state information to figure this out or the scheduling information
进程有一个创建它的父进程
a process has a parent process that created it
我们接下来会谈到这个
we'll talk about that next
可能有它创建的子进程
typically or not typically but it might have children processes that it creates
可能有同父进程创建的兄弟进程，等等
might have sibling processes that his parent also created and so on
它们具有不同的安全含义
these have different security implications
但在这节课中，我们主要讨论的是进程的创建
but mostly in this lecture we'll just talk about the creation of processes
进程有许多共享资源
a process will have a number of shared resources that it uses
文件、各种管道
files various pipes
标准输入、标准输出
such as standard input standard output
套接字，如果要用网络的话，等等
sockets if it does network communications and so forth
进程有自己的内存空间
process has its own memory space
有了它，进程就能干自己想干的
with which it can do whatever it wants
加载其他库等等
load other libraries and so forth into this
或用它的一部分
or use it as scratch bit
就是内存嘛
obviously it's just memory
进程具有安全上下文
and the process has security context
在另一节课中
in a different lecture
你们要么已经听过，要么马上就会听到
you will either have already heard or you will hear
是关于Linux安全上下文的，像用户组等等
about the Linux security context with users groups and so forth
还有一个额外的东西叫做capabilities
there's an additional thing called capabilities
它针对各进程记录
which are tracked per process
估计等我们讲到沙盒时会讲到它
most likely we will cover those when we talk about sandboxing in a different module
好的
all right
这是进程的概述
so this is a process at a nutshell
但是这些进程是从哪里来的呢
but where do these processes come from
在Linux进程中或多或少通过有丝分裂进行传播
in Linux process propagate by mitosis more or less
这是什么意思?
what does this mean
这意味着有一个原始进程
this means that you have an original process
然后发生了一些事情，有了两个进程
and then something happens and you have two process
在细胞的生物学意义上
in the biological sense with cells
旧细胞不再存在
the old cell ceases to exist
分裂成了两个新的细胞
and splits into kind of two new cells
在Linux
with Linux
这更像是克隆的场景
it's more of a cloning scenario
进程将调用一个系统功能
where a process will call an operating system functionality
一个Linux内核系统调用
a Linux kernel system call
fork或是相对新的clone
either fork or more recently clone
这两个系统调用将把该进程
these two system calls will take the process
差不多是，直接拷贝一份
and just copy it basically more or less let's say
可以简单理解为拷贝一份一模一样的
an easy way to think of it is just an exact copy
只是新进程知道自己是子进程
except for the the new process knows that as a child
旧进程成为了父进程
making the old process the parent
子进程将，如果你想
then the child if you want to
例如，如果你想在shell中执行/bin/cat
for example if you are in your shell and you want to execute /bin/cat
shell执行完fork后，会有一个父进程一个子进程
your shell will fork into a parent and a child
子进程知道自己是子进程
and then the child knowing it's a child
会用另一个系统调用clone，替换自己
will replace itself using another piece of Linux OS functionality the clone system call
它把自己替换成/bin/cat
it will replace itself with /bin/cat
这就是如何启动/bin/cat的
and that's how you launch /bin/cat
这很简单
so that's pretty straightforward
这个替换具体是什么样的呢
what does this replacing actually look like
它涉及加载/bin/cat
you know it involves loading /bin/cat
首先涉及到清空进程
at first it involves emptying out the process
这个简单，内核自己就做了
that's nice and easy the kernel does it
但当涉及到加载/bin/cat，就比较困难了
but then it involves loading /bin/cat and this is harder
首先在加载进程时
so first in the loading process
我们必须弄清楚
we have to figure out
能加载我们想加载的文件吗
can we load the file we want to load
加载失败的原因有很多
there's a number of reasons why it might fail
最常见的是权限不对
the most common one is permissions that aren't correct
例如，文件没有执行权限
for example there is no execute permissions on that file
这没问题
that's fine no problem
你可以赋个执行权限，再试一次
you can mark it as executable try it again
但一般来说，没权限时，execve会失败
but generally speaking in this scenario the execve call will fail
然后bash会提示
and then bash will tell you something
一些类似文件没权限之类的
along the lines of whatever file not executable or whatnot
假设没遇到问题
so let's say it's all okay
然后当执行execve /bin/cat时
then when you run execve /bin/cat
内核必须决定要加载的是什么
the kernel has to decide what to load
这有很多不同选择
and there are a number of different options
为了解决这个问题
in order to figure this out
内核会查看该文件
the kernel will actually look at the file
看看它是什么类型的文件
and they'll say what kind of file is it
检查开头
look at the beginning
如果文件以所谓的Shebang开头
if the file starts with what is called a Shebang
就是#!
a hash exclamation point
内核将把它当作一个脚本文件
the kernel will treat this as a script file
你通常会在shell脚本、Python脚本中看到
you generally see this with shell scripts Python scripts
但是任何脚本文件都是这样的
but any script file is like this
我们一会再讨论这个问题
and we'll play around with that in a second
内核要做的是
what the kernel will do is
从该行的其余部分提取出解释器
extract the interpreter from the rest of that line
然后用给的文件名做参数，执行这个解释器
and run that interpreter with the original file as an argument
让我们来看看这里发生了什么
let's actually take a look at what happens here
好吧
all right
假设我要执行个脚本
let's say I want to have a script
这是一个shell脚本，里面执行echo hi
and I it's a shell script and I say echo hi
启动它
let's launch it
权限被拒绝，权限检查失败
permission denied there's that permission check failing
给它执行权限
let's make it executable
再次启动
launch it again
好的，成功了
okay that worked
这就是我们的脚本/bin/sh echo hi
so there's our script /bin/sh echo hi
它确实有效
and it is it works
是这样的
so what happens was
内核查看了第一行
the kernel looks at that first line
或者说查看了前两个字节
or looks at the first two bytes really
它看到了那个#!
it sees that hash bang
然后读入那行剩下的，执行它
then it reads the rest of the line and executes that
简单
nice and simple
把这个文件名作为参数执行它
executes that with this file name as an argument
我们可以更清楚地看到这一点
we can actually see this more explicitly
如果我们把这个解释器改成/bin/echo
if we change this interpreter to something like /bin/echo
我保存这个文件
if I just save this file
/bin/echo会回显你输入的内容
/bin/echo will just echo back you know whatever you type in
如果用这个/bin/echo来执行some-script
now if you execute some-script with this /bin/echo
看一下
let me show it to you again
执行它
execute it
它输出了./some-script
and it echoes out some-script
为什么会这样呢
why does it do that
内核看到/bin/echo是脚本的解释器
well the kernel saw that /bin/echo as the interpreter of the script
然后调用了/bin/echo ./some-script
and called /bin/echo space ./some-script
就是这个
this exact thing
像这样
that
看吧
boom some-script all right
有趣的是，这可以递归
interestingly this can be recursive
这个解释器也可以是一个shell脚本
that interpreter can also be a shell script
我们看一下some-script2
so if we look at some-script2
我们创建个脚本，它调用some-script
we create something here that calls into some-script 1
给它执行权限
and we make that executable
启动它
we launch it
能看到给echo的是./some-script和./some-script2
we see echo being called with some-script one some-script2
发生了啥
so what happens here
some-script2把some-script当作解释器
well some-script 2 calls some-script as its interpreter
所以最终执行了这个
so this ends up getting executed
然后some-script调用了它的解释器echo
okay and then some-script calls echo as its interpreter
所以最终被执行了这个
so this ends up getting executed
这正是执行some-script2时的情况
and that is exactly what happens when you execute some-script2
酷
cool
非常有趣的东西
pretty interesting stuff
当然，这里也可以有参数
of course you can also have arguments here
然后它们也会作为参数传给解释器
and then they will also be passed on as arguments to the interpreter
它会把文件名作为最后一个参数
and it'll just tack on as the last argument the file name
很棒，我们继续讲进程加载
very awesome let's move on to our loading process
假设它不是一个脚本文件
all right so let's say it's not a script file
那么内核会查看一个内核配置
then the kernel moves on and looks in a kernel configuration
它在linux /proc下
which is exposed in a directory in Linux in the proc filesystem
的一个叫binfmt_misc的目录
called binfmt_misc
binfmt是一个管理如何执行文件的内核子系统
bin format is the kernel subsystem that figures out how to execute files
binfmt_misc这种方式
binfmt_misc is this sort of way
能给它任意配置来执行文件
to give it arbitrary configurations of things to execute
让我们来看看
let's take a look at that
如果我们进入/proc/sys/fs/binfmt_misc
if we go to /proc/sys/fs/binfmt_misc
能看到很多不同的配置
we see a bunch of different configurations
我这有一个jar文件的配置
so I have a configuration for jar files
因为我曾经安装了java运行环境
because I installed the Java runtime at some point
还有一堆不同架构的配置
I have a configuration for a bunch of different architectures
因为我安装了QEMU
because I've installed the Qemu user static package
如果看一下这些配置
if you look at these
比如jar文件配置
like the jar file configuration
简单明了
it's nice and simple
如果内核发现要执行文件的开头是这些字节
if it finds that a file that I'm trying to execute begins with these bytes
偏移量为0处
at offset 0 of course
就是在最开头处
so right at the beginning
如果字节是50
if I have the bytes 50
这是ASCII码 504b 0304
this is ASCII code 504b 0304
我们能看一下这些字节是什么字符
we can actually see what these bytes are
这样做
by doing 504b
是PK
that's PK
如果文件开头是字符PK
if a file starts with PK
这意味着它是一个Java包
that means it is a Java archive
然后内核会用jexec执行它
and then it is run with jexec
jexec是用来执行java包的程序
which is a program that runs a Java archive
很酷
super cool stuff
现在我可以直接./java包
now I can just dot slash a Java archive
就和执行shell脚本一样
just like I can a shell script
也和稍后讨论的二进制文件一样
or we'll talk later on a binary
有趣的是
interestingly
看一下qemu-mips的配置
if you look at this qemu-mips configuration
这个配置是执行ELF的
this is a configuration to run an ELF file
能看到ELF的文件头
you can see the header of an ELF file
这个7F，ASCII的E、L、F，都是大写的
the 7f E is in ASCII L in ASCII F in ASCII all caps
7F、E、L、F是ELF文件头中的魔数
7f E L F is the ELF file header magic number
就在ELF文件的开头
right at the beginning of the ELF file
还有一堆需要匹配的东西
and then it has a bunch of other stuff that needs to match
还有一个掩码，表示哪些要匹配，哪些不要
and then it has a mask of what needs to match and what doesn't need to match
因为一个ELF文件描述能适合很多架构
because an ELF file describes can be for a number of architectures
所以要有个掩码
so this mask on an ELF file
有了这些，其中某一位匹配意味着它是一个MIPS文件
with all of these any one bit in it matching will mean that it is a MIPS file
如果你看一下mips和mipsel
interestingly here if you look at MIPS versus MIPS little endion
它们的掩码有些许不同
there is slight difference in this mask here
在这里
there
然后它就知道了这是一个不同架构的ELF文件
and then it'll just determine okay this is an ELF file for a different architecture
我们在qemu中运行它
let's run it in qemu
它甚至通过匹配这些不同格式能找到合适的qemu
boom it figures out even the correct qemu by matching these different formats
有趣
super interesting stuff very fun to mess around with
你可以在这里设置一下
you can set things up here
让系统能用wine之类的自动执行windows可执行文件
to automatically run Windows executables through wine etc etc
放到以前我不一定推荐这么做
I wouldn't necessarily recommend that back in
最开始引入这个技术时，21世纪初还是什么时候
where these things were originally introduced like the early 2000s or something
我当时觉得binfmt_misc超级棒
the binfmt_misc I thought it was super awesome
为了自动运行PE文件，我配置了PE格式
and I configured Windows executables PE files to automatically run them
的魔数，PE......
their magic numbers PE something something something
让它能自动在wine中执行
to automatically run in wine
这一切都很棒
and this was all great
直到遇到一些疯狂的情况
until through some insane situation
最终我的Linux机器感染了Windows恶意软件
I ended up infecting my Linux box with Windows malware
因为wine足够模拟恶意软件所需的
because wine was good enough to emulate that malware
不过，这可以是一个有趣的旅程
anyways it can be an interesting journey
关键是
the point is
这里的一个要点是
one takeaway from this is
文件扩展名不重要
the file extension doesn't matter
.sh .py对于使用哪种解释器无关紧要
.sh .py does not matter for figuring out what interpreter to use
主要是看文件的开头
all that matters is the beginning of that file
好吧，我们接着看第三点
all right let's move on to No. 3
如果它不是这些binfmt_misc文件中的任何一个呢
what if it is not any of these binfmt_misc files
如果它是一个ELF，一个动态链接的ELF
what if it is an elf a dynamically-linked ELF
它开头是7F E L F
so it's a 7F elf
这与任何binfmt_misc配置都不匹配
that doesn't match any of the binfmt_misc configurations
并且是动态链接的
and is dynamic link
这意味着还要加载ELF文件依赖的库
dynamic link means that the ELF file relies on some libraries that it also needs to load
负责加载库、初始化等事物的实体
and the entity that is responsible for loading these libraries and initializing everything and so forth
称为该ELF文件的解释器
is called the interpreter of that ELF file
通俗地说就是加载器
colloquially the loader
好的，让我们
right so let's
我们接下来会深入讨论这个问题
we'll dive into that next
我还会提到静态链接ELF，它可能是最简单的了
I'll also mention a statically linked Elf is probably the simplest part of this
内核直接加载它
the kernel loads it
再跳转到ELF文件中指定的入口地址
and just jumps into the entry point specified in the ELF file
还支持其他遗留格式
other legacy formats are also supported
当然，这些是非常非常罕见的
but it is very very rare to see these of course
如前面说的，它可以递归
and these as mentioned before it can be recursive
binfmt_misc中配置的解释器可以是
a binfmt_misc interpreter can be
一个shell脚本，而脚本的解释器是一个ELF
a shell script that has an interpreter that is a normal elf
或者任何疯狂的组合
or any crazy combination
好的，我们继续
no problem alright let's run
假设你有一个动态链接的ELF
so let's say you have a dynamic linked elf
想加载，你执行它
and you want to load you're execving it
之前提到过，内核即会加载解释器
mentioned the kernel will load both the interpreter
也会加载程序，/bin/cat或别的，到内存
and the original binary the /bin/cat or whatever into memory
然后运行解释器
and then run the interpreter
现在我们来看看这个解释器
so let's look at this interpreter right now
所以
so
回到原来目录
go back
我们可以编译
we can compile
提醒一下，这是我们的cat.c
just as a reminder here is our cat.c
可以编译cat.c成cat
you can compile cat.c into cat
这是cat
now here is cat
很酷
cool
好的，它能回显我们给的数据
all right it echoes back what we put to it
也可以用它输出cat.c
or we can cat out cat.c
那现在呢
now what
现在我们看看这个ELF文件
now we can look at this elf file
我们在上节课已经做过了
we've of course done that in the binary files lecture
但我们来看看它的解释器
but let's look at cat and look at its interpreter
这是它的解释器
here's its interpreter
它就设置在其中一个头域中
it's just set in one of the headers
这就是负责加载其它库的解释器
so this is the file that gets loaded that is responsible for loading everything else
我们也可以直接执行它，指定它作为解释器
of course we can also load this file or execute it directly as a true interpreter
然后运行cat
and run cat
像这样
like this
或者输出cat.c
or of course output cat.c
这是可行的
and it works
这不是内核运行它的方式
this isn't how the kernel runs it
它不会像执行shell脚本那样，把文件名当参数执行
it doesn't run it like a shell script with the argument of the file
但这是它
but it is how
但它支持这种方法
but it does faithfully support this sort of convention
解释器也可以被更改
anyways the interpreter can also be modified
有一个叫patchelf的工具可以设置解释器
so there's a utility called patchelf that can set interpreter
比如/some/interpreter
let's say /some/interpreter
显然这是不存在的
obviously this doesn't exist
执行cat
do cat
当解释器不存在时，奇怪的事情发生了
so when the interpreter doesn't exist bizarre stuff happens
我尝试执行cat
so I tried to run cat
但bash返回没有cat这个文件或目录
and bash returns with cat no such file or directory
为什么会这样
why does this happen
这很让人沮丧
well it's a very frustrating thing
你可能为此挠破脑袋
and you might tear out a lot of hair
为此抓狂
going crazy over this
这是因为bash调用到内核
it happens because bash calls into the kernel
额，子进程执行execve调用时，进入内核
when the child process when it does execve calls into the kernel
说把我这个子进程换成/bin/cat
says hey replace me with /bin/cat
本例中，换成我们写的cat
or ./cat in this case
内核将打开cat
the kernel will open cat
看到它的解释器是/some/interpreter
it'll see its interpreter which now is /some/interpreter
发现这是一个动态链接的ELF
says oh it's a dynamically linked elf
咱们去加载这个解释器吧
let's load up this interpreter
试图打开/some/interpreter并加载到内存中
tries to open /some/interpreter and load into memory
这失败了
that fails and the kernel returns with
execve返回一个错误码，说没有这个文件
returns from execve with a failure case saying hey there's no such file
如果你看一下execve的帮助文档
so if you look at the execve man page
我们看一下返回值
and we look at return values
这里是各种可能返回的错误码
right here the various errors that can go wrong
其中一个是ENOENT
and one of them is ENOENT
文件路径名，可以是/bin/cat或cat之类的
the file pathname which is the bin cat or cat or whatever
或是脚本、ELF解释器不存在
or script or elf interpreter does not exist right
对于so库也是如此
same with shared libraries
加载so库也可能因此而失败
it can fail because of that as well
很有趣
pretty interesting
基本上就是这样的
basically what happens is that
因为某些依赖项不存在，导致加载失败
the whole loading process fails because some dependency isn't there
看看ldd能不能
and we can let's see can we do this ldd
好的，太棒了，这显然是不对的
yeah awesome so this is obviously not correct
但你能用ldd看到依赖的库
but you can see ldd and see what libraries depends on
和解释器
including the interpreter all right
这是一个非常有用的工具
this is a very useful utility
有助于弄清楚程序不能执行的原因
when you want to figure out why a program trying to run is not working
这就是解释器
so that's the interpreter
我们继续探讨
let's roll on to
解释器如何找到程序需要的库，如libc.so
how the interpreter then finds other libraries like libc.so that a program might need
再之后，我们讨论一下libc
then we'll talk about libc in a little bit later
现在我们讨论一下实际的加载过程
so let's talk about the actual loading process now
好的，内核已经加载了程序的解释器
so we've had the program the interpreter loaded by the kernel
接下来该解释器定位库了
next the interpreter locates the libraries
它通过查看好几个不同地方实现
and it does this by looking in a number of different places
这样实现是因为格式的不断演化以及兼容性等
it's a little bit of a crazy long story of evolving formats and legacy support and so forth
但是默认情况下
but by default without any extra funny business
我们只需考虑2中的步骤d和e
we just have to worry about 2d and 2e over here
2d表示在ld.so.conf系统配置中找
2d means it looks in system configuration ld.so.conf
这个配置项定义了库的可能位置
which defines all the various places libraries can be
然后尝试从那里加载库
and it tries to load libraries from there
如果失败了，它会尝试/lib和/usr/lib，以兼容老系统
and then if that fails it tries /lib and /usr/lib for old time sake
我们一般说的就是ld.so.conf
mostly we're talking about ld.so.conf
它是日常与动态链接库交互时最常见的
which is the biggest thing you'll see in your everyday interaction with dynamic link libraries
我们看一下控制库加载的其它方法
let's take a look at some of the other ways that you can mess with library loading though
LD_PRELOAD非常有名
LD_PRELOAD is a pretty well known one
你可以用一个要加载的库的路径，设置一个环境变量
you can define an environment variable with a path to a library that you can load
它将在加载其他库之前加载
that will be loaded first before any other libraries are loaded
甚至在开始执行前
and before execution goes on
这有助于调试
this is super useful for debugging
同时，在某些情况下也有安全隐患
and also has security implications in certain contexts
也可以创建LD_LIBRARY_PATH环境变量
you can create an LD_LIBRARY_PATH environment variable
这将增加一个查找库的路径
which will add an additional path in which libraries are looked for
该路径会在系统范围的配置前查找
before using the system-wide configuration
你也可以在二进制程序中控制它
and then in the binary itself you can actually mess with it
可以指定不同的库加载路径
and specify several different places to search for libraries as well
你可以
you can use
有旧的方法，也有新的
there's a legacy way and a modern way
这并不重要
doesn't really matter
我会展示新的方法
I'll show you the modern way right now
解释器找到这些库之后，就加载它们
and after the interpreter finds these libraries  it'll load them
但库可能依赖其它库
and the libraries might depend on other libraries
所以这个过程也可以递归
again this process can also be recursive
最后，库加载完后，还有一个重定位的步骤
and finally there's something called relocations after a library is loaded
它可能会用一个微妙的方式修改内存
it might need to be fixed up in subtle ways
取决于还加载了什么，以及加载到了哪里
depending on what else was loaded and where the library was loaded
重定位很复杂
these relocations can be very complicated
但基本上在某些情况下你可以理解为
but we basically in certain scenarios you might imagine that
库包含指向某些资源的指针
a library contains a pointer to some resource
如果库加载到了不同的位置
and if the library is loaded at a different location
不管库加载到了哪里
at whatever location libraries loaded
这个指针需要更新
that pointer has to be updated
这样它才能指向正确的位置
so that it points to the correct location
这大概就是重定位
these are relocations
默认情况下，库中有一堆要重定向的
and libraries have tons of them by default
我们再在终端上仔细的看一下加载过程
so let's look at the loading process in a little more detail on the terminal here
这里有cat
so here here we have again cat
可以cat输出cat.c
we can cat out
cat哪里去了
where did cat go
哦
oh
我改了解释器
I mess with the interpreter
所以cat被搞坏了
so cat is screwed
好的，我们重新编译cat
all right let's recompile cat
好的，又有cat了
all right here we have cat
很好
Boom cat.c nice and simple program
我要用一个叫strace的工具
I'm gonna use a utility called strace
strace是一个很酷的工具
strace is a very cool utility that
它能遍历并打印出程序用的所有系统调用
goes through and prints out all of the system calls the OS functionality used by a program
我们将在进程生命周期的下一讲讨论系统调用
and we'll talk about system calls unfortunately at next lecture on the process lifetime
如果我strace ./cat cat.c
so if I strace cat.c
能看到它做了很多事
you can see it does a lot of stuff
这是开头的execve系统调用
here's that execve call in the beginning
所以strace实际上是从bash的子进程中开始的
so strace actually starts up in that child process of bash
然后有一堆
then there is a various
我们这里不会深入brk
so the BRK we won't go into this right now
有很多其他的东西
there's various other stuff for setting up things
然后在这里我们加载了ld.so.cache
and then here we load this ld.so.cache
它实际上是ld.so.conf编译后的版本
which is actually a compiled version of this ld.so.conf
不用管他
again don't worry about it
基本上它会查看这里列出的每一条路径
basically it looks at every path listed here
先试了这个
tries this first
它成功了
it succeeds
然后你可以看到
and then here you can see
它读出了这个库，查看了其中的各种属性
it's reading out this library to see various properties in it
这里是，这个是八进制的0x7F
and here is that this is 7f in Octal
ELF
elf cool
它找到了libc，然后运行它
so it finds libc and then it runs it
帅
awesome
我们来谈谈LD_PRELOAD
let's talk about LD_PRELOAD
通过LD_PRELOAD，你可以
so with LD_PRELOAD you can actually
给一个库中的函数，覆盖后面加载的库中函数
set a library to run and override functions of future loaded libraries
我写了一个preloader
I wrote an preloader
它替换了read函数
that replaces read with a function
它将pwned写入缓冲区并返回所写入的大小
that writes pwned into the buffer and returns the size that it wrote
所以无法再用read读入其它东西了
so you won't be reading anything anymore
只能读入pwned
we'll just read in pwned
我们 LD_PRELOAD
so let's do LD_PRELOAD
先编译它
let's compile it first
把它编译成一个so库
so we compile it as a shared library
现在我们可以执行它了
okay and now we can execute it
带上路径
with a path
它至少需要一些路径
it needs at least some path
否则它会在常规的
otherwise it'll search for it in a normal
我记得它会在常规的库路径查找
I think it'll search for it in the normal library path
但不确定
but don't quote me on that
然后执行 ./cat cat.c
and then let's call cat cat.c
没输出cat.c的内容
and instead of cat.c
只看到了一遍遍地输出pwned
we just see pwned over and over and over
因为read一直返回6，不返回EOF
because of course it just keeps returning
所以cat会一直输出
so cat keeps printing it
酷
very cool stuff
如果我们要strace它
if we strace this instead
strace有一个-E 参数
and strace has a dash capital E
它会在执行程序之前，设置环境变量
where it'll set the environment variable before executing the program
如果我们这样做
if we do this here like this
那么就成了设置strace的LD_PRELOAD库了
then we'll LD_PRELOAD strace itself
这不是我们想要的
and that's not what we want
这会搞砸一切
because that'll mess everything up
所以我们执行 strace -E
so we do this strace dash capital E
我们运行它
we run that and
我们重定向一下
let's redirect this
就看看头几个系统调用
look at just the first bunch of syscalls
这个是execve
here's that execve
一切都很好
everything is great
有一点要知道的
actually one thing to know
这里说有57个环境变量被传入
this says 57 environment variables that are being passed
因为这是一个环境变量
because this is an environment variable of course
如果我们直接strace ./cat cat.c
if we just do strace cat.c
56个环境变量
we'll see 56 environment variables
所以正如我们预计的，它是一个额外的环境变量
right so that's an extra environment variable past as expected
这里输出了一堆pwned
here's a bunch of pwned being written out
这里有一件有趣的事情
here's an interesting thing
它在这里打开的preload.so
here's where it opens this preload.so
加载它，之后再加载libc
loads it and then later on it goes on to load libc
很酷
pretty cool stuff
好吧
okay
现在看看LD_LIBRARY_PATH
now LD_LIBRARY_PATH
这是另一个可以利用的
it's another thing you can do
我们就粗略地看一下
and we're just gonna do a cursory look
我们去掉LD_PRELOAD
so let's take LD_PRELOAD out
你可以在这里设置一个路径
you can set a path here
现在cat所依赖的每一个库
and now every library that cat depends on
我们都将先从/some/library/path中找
we will first try to load it from this /some/library/path
它试着很有创意
and it tries to be fairly creative with
它尝试了很多它需要的东西的变体
where it tries a lot a bunch of variants of what it needs and
这里/some/library/path/libc.so.6
and then here /some/library/path/libc.so.6
当然所有的这些文件或目录都不存在
of course all of these there's no such file or directory
我没有创建过/some/library/path
I didn't create /some/library/path/blah
然后它继续查找默认目录
so then it goes on to the default
顺便提一下ld.so.preload
cool also mention by the way ld.so.preload
如果它存在
if this exists
就可以为整个系统指定LD_PRELOAD库
you can list LD_PRELOAD libraries for the whole system
这要非常小心，这是一个很容易搞坏一切的操作
be very careful this is a very easy way to break everything
因为如果你用了破坏正常功能的库
because if you put some library that screws functionality
并放在了ld.so.preload中
as listed into ld.so.preload
你将无法执行任何程序
you can very quickly cease to be able to run anything
比如VI之类的，来撤销你的操作
like VI or whatever to undo it
酷
cool
好的
all right
还有一件事要看
one thing left to look at
runpath和rpath
run path and rpath
我们只看run path
we are just look at run path there
这里一个是另一个的新的版本
one is a new version of the other essentially
你可以用patchelf设置rpath
you can use the patchelf utility to set rpath
这实际上是设置run path
this actually sets the run path
如果你加上 --force-rpath
if you do force rpath
它才会设置rpath
it'll actually set rpath
你可以把它设为任意值
and you can also set this to wherever
它会在这里找库
where to look for libraries
然后./cat
and you do cat
好的
okay
我们再运行一次
now we'll run the same thing
看看区别
and just to see the the differences here
尝试在我们的LD_LIBRARY_PATH找了libc
that's our LD_LIBRARY_PATH that is being used to try to search for libc
没找到
it doesn't find libc
然后它尝试在run path中找libc
then it searches for this run path for libc
也没找到
doesn't find it there
没这个目录
no such directory
然后看了ld.so.cache
and then it looks at ld.so.cache
并在第一个配置的位置找到了它
and finds it in the first configured place
很酷
very cool stuff
粗略地说，这是库的加载顺序
roughly speaking this is the library loading order
我们看一下都用上会怎样
let's see what happens when we have everything
包括rpath、LD_LIBRARY_PATH和LD_PRELOAD
the rpath the LD_LIBRARY_PATH and LD_PRELOAD
我们加个没有的
let's just do something that's not there
这样不影响执行
so that it doesn't mess with our execution
当然，首先它会尝试加载LD_PRELOAD
so of course first it tries to load our LD_PRELOAD
我们没指定路径
and we didn't set a path
所以它尝试从别的地方加载
so tries to load it from everywhere
包括LD_LIBRARY_PATH和run path
including the LD_LIBRARY_PATH and the run path
然后它尝试加载libc
and then it tries to load libc
不对，这个是haha.so
nope that's little haha
哇，它尝试了很多地方
wow it's trying to load a lot from everywhere
还有/lib/x86_64
from here /lib/x86_64
这就是最坏的情况了
so it's just the whole worst scenario
抱歉，我不是故意让大家陷入这种境地的
sorry I didn't mean to send us down this path rabbit hole
但还是到了
but we went
然后查看了LD_PRELOAD
and then it looks at LD_PRELOAD
然后就找到了libc，都没看
then it finds libc without looking at
有趣
interesting
似乎覆盖了
seems that overwrites
要是我们改成./preload.so呢
what if we actually have ./preload.so
好吧
okay yeah
很有趣，很有趣
interesting that was an interesting
好吧
all right
不知道怎么回事
I don't know what happened there
但能看到preload被加载了
but you can see preload gets loaded
先处理的LD_PRELOAD
the LD_PRELOAD runs first
然后查找并加载库
and then all the rest of the library resolution and loading
先从LD_LIBRARY_PATH的内容开始
starting with things in the LD_LIBRARY_PATH
再看run path中的
then in the run path
然后看系统范围的配置
then in the system wide configuration
很酷，好吧
very cool all right
这些库被加载好了
so these libraries get loaded
这可能也加载了别的东西
potentially this causes other stuff to get loaded as well
然后我们有一个问题
and then we have the question of
这些都加载到哪里去了
where does it all get loaded into
这是一个有趣的问题
this is an interesting question
我前面提到过，进程的虚拟内存空间
I mentioned earlier the processes' virtual memory space
系统上有大量的进程
of course you have tons of process on your system as mentioned
所有的东西都有自己的进程之类的
everything can be its own process and so forth
所有这些进程都需要隔离
all of these processes need to be isolated
否则就没有安全保障
otherwise there's no security
如果你的电子游戏能扰乱你的
if your video games can start messing with your
啥呢
I don't know whatever
没想到好的例子
I'm not gonna come up with the scenario
但默认情况下，进程不应该干扰彼此的内存
but processes shouldn't be able to mess with each other's memory by default
除非配置了capabilities之类的
without additional capabilities or additional actions and so forth
所以每个进程都有自己的虚拟内存空间
so every process has its own virtual memory space
这里说的是现代多进程操作系统
this is the case in more or less all modern multi process operating systems
进程的这个空间里装着二进制文件
and this space for a process will contain the binary
比如cat /bin/cat之类的
such as cat /bin/cat or whatever
它的库
its libraries
还有用于malloc的堆
and it has the heap for dynamic alloced memory
用于存放局部变量、返回地址和控制数据等的栈
a stack for local function variables and return addresses and control data and so forth
程序的其它辅助内存映射区
any other memory map by the program helper regions
在每个虚拟内存空间的上半部分
and in the top half of every virtual memory space
是内核内存，不同进程内核区数据可能不同
kernel memory potentially specialized for that process
这些虚拟内存实际存储在精心挑选的物理内存页
all of this virtual memory resides in physical memory in carefully mapped locations
因此，你机器上运行的多个进程的虚拟内存
so every process running at the same time actively running on your machine
都在物理内存空间中
has some virtual memory in your physical memory space
但显然不是按虚拟内存地址挑选的（映射的）
but it's obviously not mapped according to its virtual addresses
一个进程可能在虚拟内存中用了0x80,000
a process could reserve 0x80,000 in its virtual memory space
另一个进程也可能在自己的虚拟内存中用它
the other process might reserve that in the other process's memory space
但它们实际上位于物理内存的不同地址
but they'll actually be located in different places in physical memory
它由内核
with some mapping that the kernel keeps track of
或者说内存管理子系统记录
or the memory management subsystem keeps track of
并解决如何从虚拟内存转换到物理内存
to figure out how to direct virtual memory access to physical memory
你可以通过查看/proc/self/maps来查看进程虚拟内存空间
point is you can see a process's memory space by looking in /proc/self/maps
我们来看一看
let's take a look
我们可以cat /proc/self/maps
so we can do cat /proc/self/maps
这是cat的虚拟内存空间
and this is the memory space of cat
它把我的cat放到了这里的几个内存页
so it loads my cat binary into a couple of different pages here at
内核把它加载在0x555...
the kernel load it here at 555
这是一个随机生成的内核地址(口误)
this is a randomly generated kernel address
如果我再运行一次
if I run it again
不是内核地址
not kernel address
是一个随机生成的虚拟地址
a randomly generated virtual address
内核把二进制文件放在这里
that the kernel chose to place my binary at
内核也用mmap选择一个地址
kernel also chose a address from using mmap
来放解释器
to place my loader at
之后的库加载在这地址之前
and then future libraries are loaded right before that address
要是依赖更多的库的话
you know if I had more and more binaries that is depended on
我们看一下实际的cat
let's look at the real cat
我不清楚
I don't know
它可能依赖同样数量的库
it probably depends on the same number of libraries
它多出来一个locale库
but it has an additional locale information
我猜是用于帮助功能
I guess for the help functionality
它在libc的地址之前加载，等等
that it loads before libc and so forth
之后的内存映射会继续选在7f地址区处
future mappings will keep filling in the 7F area
进程在随机地址处还有一个栈
then a process also has a stack at a random location
这个程序没用任何malloc之类的函数
and this doesn't use any allocation
所以没有创建堆区
so the heap space didn't get created
用了动态内存分配的进程，会有堆
but something that uses dynamic memory allocation will have a heap
还有一些其他的东西
and there's some other stuff
内核映射的辅助的虚拟的库
helper libraries virtual libraries mapped in by the kernel
不在本课的讨论范围
which we won't talk about in this lecture
只要知道有这么个东西就行
but just be aware that they are there
这就是虚拟内存空间
so that is a kernel's virtual memory space
如果你感兴趣，你可以去这里进一步阅读
if you're interested you can go to this resource here and read further
好的
alright
我一直提到libc这个，libc那个
I keep mentioning libc this libc that
我们在刚刚的内存映射中看到了libc
and we saw libc a bunch of times in for example the memory mappings right here
libc是什么东西
what the hell is libc
Libc是一个充满辅助函数的库
libc is a library full of helper functions
几乎每个程序都用它
that is used by almost every program
几乎每个程序都链接了它
or linked by almost every program
说的有点不太准确
I have almost every process on the size that's inaccurate
它被加载后，几乎每个程序都把它链接到几乎每个进程
it gets loaded as a result of being linked by almost every program into almost every process
里面有很多你认为理所当然的功能
and there's a bunch of functionality that you take for granted
如果你用过c，你肯定用过printf
if you've used c you've used printf
它就在libc中
that's in libc
还有scanf
scanf
malloc和free
malloc and free
整个动态分配库都是libc的一个子功能
that whole allocator library is a sub component of libc
还有很多你很可能没听过的东西
a lot of crazy stuff that you you likely haven't seen
libc有很多东西
libc has a lot of things
哦，好的
oops all right
它是最常见的库
it's again the most common library seen in these
至少在Linux上
on Linux at least
静态链接的加载过程要简单得多
statically link binaries have a much simpler loading process
直接加载就行
they just get loaded
我们看一下静态链接版本的cat
right so let's take a look at a statically link version of cat
这个cat-static
so here is cat-static
你可以用它输出./cat的源码
you can of course cat out the source code
我们还可以
we can
它的功能完全一样，不同之处在于
it works exactly the same the difference is
你看一下cat-static和cat占用的字节大小
if you look at how many bytes cat-static versus cat takeup
差别很大
it is huge
cat的大小是22KB
cat is 22 kilobytes compiled
cat-static几乎要1MB
cat-static is almost a megabyte
我还真没想到./cat这么小
and I'm actually shocked at that small
如果你用cat-static看一下/proc/self/maps
but cat-static if you look at /proc/self/maps
简单多了
much much simpler
没映射库
there are no libraries mapped in
分配了堆
heap is allocated
我想这就是发生了
I guess this is something that happens
我不知道为什么这里用了堆
I'm not sure why heap is allocated here
但在非静态链接的版本中没用
but not in the non static version
我猜可能是初始化的过程不太一样
I'm guessing there's just a different set of initialization routines that run
我们接下来会讲到这些
we'll get to those next
反正它更简单
but it's simpler
没有库
there are no libraries
因为是静态链接的
because statically linked binary
为什么我们不出于简单的目的全都用静态链接
why don't we ship everything statically linked for simplicity
我的意思是，文件大小的区别重要吗
I mean what is this difference in file size （matter）
你可能会说，这在今天已经无关紧要了
you might argue it's not really relevant nowadays
用共享库可以实现很多技巧，进程间共用内存等等
but there are various tricks that can be done with sharing library memory across processes and so forth
但在如今这个拥有大量内存的时代，这一点越来越不重要了
but that is less and less critical nowadays in the age of a lot of memory
有很多空内存
and a lot of dry space
事实上，像rust这样的语言
and in fact languages such as rust
大部分支持静态链接
mostly support static linking
rust、要使用C库，你，抱歉
rust to use C libraries you sorry
你可以在rust中使用C库
you can use C libraries and use them in rust
但rust的库是静态链接的
but rust libraries are linked statically
所以也许我们会更向这边靠拢
so maybe we'll move more in that direction
我不知道
I don't know
两种情况都存在
both cases exist
目前不用静态链接库的一个原因是
one reason until recently not to use static libraries was
静态链接的二进制文件安全性更低
less or statically linked binaries was less security opportunities
这么说不是很正确，但大体没问题
I mean this is slightly less true but still true
如果你看动态链接的情况
if you look at the dynamic case
cat被加载到这个地址
you have cat which is loaded into this crazy address
库加载在这里
and you have the libraries which are loaded into this crazy address
两者在了不同的地址区域
there are different addresses
你不能
you can't actually
知道cat的加载地址，无法推出库的地址
by knowing where cat is loaded you can't know where the libraries are loaded
除非你在写你的程序中记录了库的地址
unless your cat knows where its libraries are
但通常，甚至在进程运行时
but oftentimes even during execution
你可能知道库加载在哪里
you might know where the libraries are loaded
但不知道cat在哪里
but not where cat is loaded
现在，这里的库是挨着加载的
right now the way things are the libraries are loaded right up against each other
所以当你知道了ld的地址，可以推出libc的地址，反之亦然
so you can know knowing ld you can know where libc is and vice versa
但这不是一定的
but there's no reason that has to be the case
你也可以把它们加载到完全随机化的偏移地址
you could load them at completely randomized offsets as well
对于静态链接的二进制文件，就不行
for a static link binary of course you can't do that
能看到它加载在这个地址
you'll notice it's loaded at this address
这个地址在每次执行的时候不会发生变化
and this address does not change over executions
栈和堆会变
I mean the stack and heap still change
但cat一直加载在0x40000
but cat is loaded at 40000
最近我们不打算
recently we're not gonna try
为什么不呢
why not
我们来试试
let's try it
有一个-static-pie参数
there is a static pie
我不知道这能不能成
I have no idea this will work
以前没用过
I've never done this before
天呐。
holy shit
最近
recently
PIE代表位置无关代码
PIE stands for Position Independent Code
引入这个技术是为了让静态链接库支持位置无关特性
this was introduced to allow statically linked libraries to be position independent
这很酷
so that's pretty cool
不记得我有没有提过
I don't remember if I actually mentioned why
静态链接是什么
what makes a statically linked binary statically linked
它表示把所有的库，如libc，都打包进一个程序
it is that all of the libraries like libc are included inside this same binary
这就是为什么它这么大
that's what makes it big
但这也意味着，知道了程序加载地址
but it also means that knowing the position of this binary
同时你就知道了libc的地址和其它库的地址
you also know the position of libc and all the other libraries
这是静态链接和动态链接库之间的安全差距
that's a security gap between statically and dynamic linked libraries
另一方面
on the other hand
动态链接的程序也有很多可以被利用的安全问题
there are various security problems with dynamically linked binaries that can be taken advantage of
所以这是一种取舍
so it's a trade off
无论好坏
for better or worse
标准Linux发行版中的大多数程序
the majority of the programs in a standard linux distribution
都是动态链接的
are going to be dynamically linked
好的，接下来看什么
all right let's see what we got next
初始化
initialization
这是我们今天要讲的最后一个
so this is the last step that we'll talk about today
在所有东西都加载到内存之后
after everything is loaded into memory and so forth
就该初始化了
it is initialize
每个elf，二进制文件和库，都可以指定构造函数
every elf binary and library can specify constructors
这是代码结构，不对
this is code constructure sorry
可以指定在程序实际启动之前运行的代码
this is code that runs before the program is actually launched
因此，有的版本的libc会初始化堆的内存
so depending on the version, libc can initialize memory regions for dynamic allocations
所以之前在静态链接的例子中，看到了堆内存
so we saw a heap show up here in the statically linked case
哦，我忘记切换到幻灯片了，抱歉
oops I forgot switch the slides sorry about that
我到底搞砸了多少
so how much did I screwed that up
我们回来
let's come back okay
我们之前看到这里
you saw this yeah yeah we saw this
这很重要
this is important
好的，初始化
all right initialization
构造函数在程序开始执行之前运行
constructors run before the program execution start
执行在main之前
before main is executed
你可以指定自己的构造函数
and you can specify your own constructors
好的，我们可以编辑cat.c
right so we can edit cat.c
现在我们要看这个画面
and again now we want this
我们可以编辑cat.c
we can edit cat.c
可以这样写
and we can say attribute constructor
好的，它会输出haha
alright and it'll just print haha
编译它，不管是不是静态链接
and if you compile this statically or not
然后执行它
and execute it
我们将在main执行前看到haha
we'll see haha before main is executed
这对LD_PRELOAD特别有用
this is especially useful for LD_PRELOAD
我们来看看preload.c
so let's look at our preload.c
这是我们的pwned
this is our pwned
现在我们放入这个构造函数
now we put in this constructor
我们编译
we compile
然后运行
and then we run
带上 LD_PRELOAD
with an LD_PRELOAD
我们只看头几个
let's just get the first okay
我们没重编译preload.c
we didn't compile the preload.c
什么情况
what happened
好的
okay preload
编译成功了
that works
用了preload
gets preload
就是没输出haha
that did not get printed
我暂停一下录音
let me pause the recording
弄清楚后再给你们答复
figure this out and get back to you
我回来了
and we are back
很抱歉
sorry about that
我明白了
I figured it out
在原来的版本中
in the original version
在我的幻灯片上
in what I have on the slides
我们看一下幻灯片
let me show you the slides
我们用的puts
we have puts been used
puts中有缓存问题
there was some sort of crazy caching problem in puts
准确地说，是在这个libc版本中
or in libc with this
可以用fflush解决这个问题
so flushing works
但我直接换了另一种方法
but I replaced it with a different solution
我马上展示给你们
I will show you
我提到过
I mentioned that
好吧，我没提过
well I didn't mention
有一个很棒的计算机科学笑话
there's an awesome computer science joke
在计算机科学中有两个尚未解决的问题
that there are two unsolved problems in computer science naming
抱歉今天上太多课了
shit sorry too much lecturing today
命名、[缓存doge]以及off-by-1问题
naming caching and off by 1 errors
好吧
all right
我们继续
let's move on
我指给你们哪里出错了
so let me show you what went wrong
以及我是如何修复它的
and how I fixed it
这是修改后的preload.c
here is the new fixed preload.c
在haha函数中
so in the haha func
好吧，你能看到在我调试的过程中
well you can see in my debugging process
我还检查了是不是函数名的问题
I also checked if the name was a problem
构造函数现在叫wtf
so the constructor now called wtf
以前用的puts
used to have puts
现在改成了write，直接绕过了
I just changed it to use write directly to bypass all of this
缓存失效
this cache invalidation
计算机科学中的两个未解问题，缓存
two unsolved problems in computer science caching
该死的，又没讲顺
god damn it
命名[缓存失效]和off-by-1错误
naming [cache invalidation] and off-by-1 errors
不管怎样
anyways
使用write直接绕过libc的puts问题
if you use write directly bypass libc funny business with puts
就行
it works
编译一下
so let's compile
然后我们用这个执行LD_PRELOAD
okay and then we do the LD_PRELOAD with this
我们可以看到
and we see that
输出pwned前，先输出了haha
there is a haha gets printed before all the pwned
这很好
so this this is neat here
当你有机会
but every once in a while you have the opportunity
向进程中注入库
to inject the library into a process
例如，使用某个不小心暴露的功能
using uncarefully exposed functionality for example
在这种情况，能在库加载时先运行代码
it is super useful in those cases to be able to run code on  library load
而不必一直等库函数被调用，是非常有用的
without having to wait until functions of your library invoked
好吧
all right
就是这些
that is it
这就是我们今天要讨论的关于进程生命周期的全部
that's all of the process lifetime that we're gonna talk about today
这堂课的时间远超我的预期
this lecture we ran way longer than I intended
我的很多课都是这样
this is the case for a lot of my lectures
我很抱歉
I apologize
希望现在你对进程的加载有了更深刻的理解
hopefully you now have a very good understanding of how process is loaded
理解了程序是如何变成进程的
or how program becomes a process
它自己先被加载、依赖库被加载、然后初始化
essentially it's loaded the libraries are loaded and it's initialized
好的
all right
在进程生命周期余下部分——它的执行过程中再见
I will see you next time on the rest of this process runtime on how it actually executes
多谢观看
thank you